Worth of profit, which has generated New Zealand as a percentage of
GDP versus what happens in Australia.
So, it's quite a big number, and no wonder there is a committee about that.
So let's talk about some of the things that are symptoms.
And I know that you were speaking to Revolut and others earlier this morning.
So nearly 87% of deposits sit with the Big Four.
And that means that you have a very strong concentration of the funding base that
these banks use. Let's also talk about the fact that these banks enjoy
top quartile returns, and I think it's fair to say there's no evidence that they
take more risk than Australian banks, yet generate quite considerably better
returns.
So I think when you think about that, you sort of wonder what's the difference
there. You can also say, without a shadow of a doubt, that they enjoy
top quartile efficiency, usually measured by cost of income.
But I think as even the previous bank was answering, we've been late with
functionality. So generally speaking, you might ask yourself, are
they cheaper to run because we don't bring the new functionality soon enough?
Last couple of things I just wanted to touch on.
So,
there is very high inertia. So the numbers that we're talking about with open
banking swapping, if you have a look at the UK number, more than two-thirds of the
people swapping are the same people swapping all the time.
So they'll move from Nationwide Bank for 250 quid, and they'll move to Revolut for
a sausage roll and a cup of coffee and a train rail, get a RAM pass,
and the next one and the next one. I'm not trying to put any shade on those offers
because customers value them, and they move to them.
Some of those banks have quite high income based on subscription services, but like
all subscription services, people value them, and they stay there.
There is actually very low transparency in lending pricing, and
so fixed-term rates and the amount of deals that are done off card
are the real competitive market, not the ones that we will see if we walk down
Lambton Quay.
And if you think about
what that means, it means that it's very difficult to get scale for fintechs
because they can't attract the deposit base, and therefore have a high-cost income.
I also just want to touch on something which I think you've done a really good job
of highlighting, the FMA transparency about the pass on.
I'd also point to the ACCC in Australia and one of their findings.
So if the ACCC in Australia knows that 70% of
savers regularly miss their bonus rate.
So you heard from Ben talking about the ANZ Serious Saver.
You need to make a minimum deposit per month, which I think is 20.
And if you do that, you'll enjoy 1.75% interest.
If, however, you don't make the $20 deposit, or you withdraw once, you
get 0.05 of a percent.
So there is a 170-point difference between the advertised rate on that
account and what 70%, based on Australian numbers, people actually receive.
So I don't think there's any reason that this committee or an
FMA couldn't ask for publishing of who actually does enjoy the rates
that they think they're going to get.
Our own State of the Savings survey showed at least that half of New Zealanders
understood how those hoops and hurdles worked.
And so I think that's a great example of where the banks have generated a set of
products which work really well for them and not very
well for seven out of 10, based on Australian numbers,
customers. And so,
without being too pointy, it is called the Serious Saver,
but it's certainly serious money for banks, and I think is a great
example of where if you want to be competitive, the transparency and the
pass-through and who enjoys it and who doesn't is something that within the powers
of the
building up the road. So, open up for questions.
I'll just kick off with a sup, if I could, on that point about the pass-through and
how if they miss the deposit or they withdraw, they lose it.
Mm-hmm.
Have you or is the bank using any of the fintech bolt-ons
to sort of scrape that information and let the customer know?
Or how do we bring more transparency to that from an open banking perspective?
Yeah. I was actually looking at a
pretty new startup
this morning, Chair, who actually was thinking about the way that they could use
the open rails to work out if their interest wasn't
credited, what was the trigger that would then alert the customer and try and move
them. So I think it's a great example of the type of
innovation that can happen. Doesn't happen at the moment.
I think most of us will receive some form of
tag or, and taking Nancy's point about whether you want a phone call or not, but,
some sort of jog that actually maybe your account and your money could work harder
for you. But if I think if a bank comes and sits in front of you and say,
"We've given 200,000 prompts to Arena and people like here as
our customers that there's a better way to save," then there shouldn't be any
problem about presenting that in a transparent way.
Mm-hmm.
Like, how many people acted on that actionable insight?
What is the effective rate that people are really receiving?
And I think the Australian, there's been a journey.
They first of all talked about customer numbers, then they talked about the volume
of customers and the amounts, all of those things.
There are available options, which I think make us more competitive.
So I know you've got three, I think three apps with Kiwi.
Mm-hmm.
But none of them would do this sort of a level of-
No, not at the moment, but I think that's the opportunity.
Yeah.
And there's a great saying that the fintechs talk about, which is, "Your margin is
my opportunity." And so I think, that is the case
that people will go into that. That's a very big number-
Yeah
... in terms of the opportunity for customers.
But again, it'll be catalyzing the interest from the customers, doing so safely,
and then the customer seeing the benefit of that.
So I think it's a bit of a three-legged-
Nice
... journey.
Is yours a sup, Dave?
No, new one.
Okay. I'll go to Irina, and then I'll come to you if it's all right.
Can I pick up on your point about the ACCC getting close to making a finding
of something that looked like gouging or excessive pricing right now, but that 2023
finding,
that was about,
strategically pricing deposits to minimize funding costs.
Is that what you think is going on in the New Zealand market?
That was a finding that complex and opaque pricing made comparison harder and
helped sticky customers to Dan Baldwi's question.
I think that complexity supports margin-
Yeah
... if that's the question. Yeah, I think it does, because it's very hard to get
price transparency and compare offers because you're often pricing
different terms. I'm talking from a customer perspective.
You might be pricing different terms.
You might not also know what the off-card negotiated rate is.
So, the rate that you see outside, is that really the best rate I can get?
What is the cash back offer if I push really hard?
Will I get a different answer from
someone sitting here if I don't?
Across the table, each of us will be better at negotiating than others.
Is that the best way to compare things?
So I think the short answer to your question is yes.
I think the best solution is to be requiring us all to put that
information out in the public arena, and then people can look.
And I think what you'll see is very strong adjustment quite quickly, because no one
will want to be an outlier on that basis.
That's a good point.
Sorry, just to answer your question, though, I think it is fair that all banks will
be looking at all of their various funding sources to try and make sure they
support their balance sheet growth.
Yeah.
And I think that's logical and expected.
Just on the change that the technology will bring.
Mm-hmm.
You can hear me puzzling about how much of
this problem is actually a technology problem.
And for 15 years, we've had banks that haven't had an incentive to invest,
including Kiwibank-
Yeah, sure
... which is very forthright with its
one
strategic stakeholder, but it wants to invest in its technology
advance program. What is government's role in
ensuring that consumers are also getting up-to-date systems for their
banking, which is a critical service?
Yeah, I
know I'm beating this drum, but I think the more transparent and the
more easily people can compare will be the
thing that will drive investment.
So, can you be in a situation where if you've got the right
technology stack, you might be optimizing the returns for your account,
you might be able to change the settings yourself.
That's not possible, as you heard from Antonia, on 30-year-old tech.
You just can't do that safely without getting yourself in-- You
haven't passed on the right promises that you'd work.
So, I think that being super clear about what the
competition looks like and what the benefits people can receive are, will drive the
investment. But certainly it's a
super interesting challenge around how you bring more people into the system, but
do so safely. And the system sort of works because everyone's
got the same set of rules and the same sort of philosophies
around the way that they protect customers.
But it's also a big barrier and a burden to new entrants.
Yeah.
And that's that same question about scale, which is--
And I think I heard earlier today there was a conversation about confirmation of
payee, for instance.
Yeah.
So confirmation of payee, it's a zero-sum game.
It just recovers its costs.
And I think if you ask why it costs ten times more than some other markets, it's
because it's one tenth of the size.
And so pushing to make sure that the pass-on costs are
transparent, pushing to make sure that as more people come, that price goes
down.
Mm-hmm.
I think you can really force the issue on that, and that's what I think we should
expect from
government and from MB and others.
I think at the moment it's pretty new and it's pretty subscale.
I think it should get cheaper and better.
I think there's an interesting question which new
entrants say, "Well, I shouldn't have to pay for everything that you've paid for."
Yeah.
Now, and in some markets that might be right.
And I think that's places like Singapore and other with the sandbox have
done a better job of saying, "We'll get you started.
We'll be proportionate while you get started." But once you get, say, in New
Zealand, that level might be 20 million or 50 million or whatever it is, you
pick the number, then from then you have to step up and carry on doing these
things.
Yeah.
But levies can't be the same for everyone, otherwise you're never going to get any
innovation.
Exactly.
The levies we face, we're looking forward next year will be, we think, something
like $14.5 million from all the various entities.
That's pretty close to 6% of our impact.
If I'm a new starter,
and I'm going out to raise capital from you, and a big chunk of that money is to
get started on the levies, you're going to stifle innovation for sure.
And so I think that's an example where COFR and others can be more
proportionate. And if you're a bigger bank and you've been at it for
25 years like us, I think, without being too crude about it, you just have to suck
it up and say, "We want a more competitive system." We've had the advantage,
particularly for us with our stakeholder and owner.
Actually,
we should let new people in.
Rock on, Steve. I just have one more question. It's a different question.
Only one?
You've got to go in a couple of minutes.
Are you in an acquisition phase of startups?
Confirmation of payee is a good example of where several
players are working with a startup.
But lots of the big banks have adopted a system where they can tell that their
technology that new entrants have is far superior
to the systems that they're running.
You heard Antonia say we're a bit envious of some of these guys who got to start
afresh. Why don't you just buy them?
Yeah, buying them is a pretty expensive exercise for a bank because of the way
that our regulatory settings work.
I think you can get the same benefit by partnering.
Mm-hmm.
For instance, we talked last time, I think, about we know that we need to have an
offering that can get money from a Kiwibank account safely
to the 160 odd wallets that are around the world.
Now, we will never be as good as Airwallex or Visa at doing that.
But we don't need to. You don't care who does it.
Behind the scenes, you want it to be safe, you want it to work through your app,
and you want it to arrive in the wallet in Indonesia or wherever, China, wherever
you're sending it, for example, safely and at a low cost.
And we can partner to do that. We don't need to build it.
So, I think the answer for us is we know that this fifth biggest
bank in New Zealand can't build all this stuff itself.
And we're all in for partnering, because it's going to allow us to go faster.
And regardless of whether you make $2 billion or not, you'll never be better at
international payments than Wise.
Yeah.
And so you've just got to jump in.
We're going to go to David Wilson next.
Yeah. So just a slightly different tack change here, Steve.
Thank you. 87% in deposits by the Big Four.
Mortgages are not far behind that, are they?
No.
So my question goes to the net interest margins, which
we understand are very high compared to the rest of the OECD.
Where are the Big Four banks getting their capital from?
And I don't think it's just because the OCR changes.
No, as you can say, the size of the
savings base is
I think it's nearly $500 billion, and they have
a massive, or 86% of that $500 billion.
Yeah.
That's a core funding element to it.
And they generate really significant profits, which means that retained earnings
mean that any capital ask is pretty easily fulfilled.
Yeah.
And we've seen,
I'm sorry I can't remember the number, but that we've seen I think something like
2.3 or $2.4 billion repatriated to the Australian parents.
Yeah.
And still have extraordinarily strong capital bases.
So
it's one-way traffic. There's no capital coming back?
No. Well, I think to be fair, they do retain a huge amount.
They are very, very big businesses, and New Zealand needs them
to be here and needs them to be active.
I think the question is,
are the returns justified by the risk that they're taking?
Yeah.
And that pressing for
different lending other than home loan lending and making its way into small,
medium businesses is probably the best chance to put that capital to work from a
New Zealand Inc. perspective.
Thank you. Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you.
I was intrigued by what you said about the experience in other
countries with open banking, the extent to which people don't shift banks-
Yep
... and the inertia there. But you said some people do.
Yep.
Do you think there's enough
switching happening at the margins to keep banks competitive,
or do you-
Yeah. I think there is in,
particularly in home loans.
Right.
I think that works. I don't think open banking is a big driver of it,
Dr. Russell. I think
the ones I spoke about in the UK are perennial switchers, so they'll be chasing the
opportunity-
Mm
... that comes from banks putting themselves into acquisition mode.
But I don't think there's any doubt that in New Zealand that if you go to a
mortgage broker, you'll lack for having one or two, three competitive offers.
So I think
it's a different mechanism-
Mm
... that I think drives competition there.
And perhaps if we see more advisors in the business banking market, that'll
accelerate that as well. But at the moment, it's pretty human-centered.
The inertia for
people, which is obviously the key battle we've got, which is get you interested
enough that you want to bank Kiwi-
Mm
... is really difficult. So we did some numbers around people picking a savings
account.
More than 65% of people only considered one area,
one provider.
So, that's what you're up against, which is if you bank with whoever you bank with,
that's where you tend to go. And so, I think by understanding and
providing more transparency, we can help, but I don't think open banking
has really been the big driver. But it can
help. And I think
it'll be really good for people choosing a second and third bank for a particular
need, maybe not switching the whole thing, and maybe that'll be the battleground.
And that might be enough.
Yep.
Thank you.
Sorry, you had a question, Todd.
A quick one.
Okay.
Yeah. Totally another different topic.
Obviously, yeah, you've been going through your own
technology transformation. Maybe just give us a quick oversight of how that's
going. Obviously, yeah, you're on-
Yeah. Look, I'm thrilled to say that on my own app, I'm
banking my savings on
our new stack, which is Thought Machine, which is
generally seen as the world-leading native cloud core.
We're about to really accelerate that in literally in the next couple of days
into more customers. Got about 1,000 of our team members
and friends and family operating on the new stack.
That's a really big step. The way I'd sort of talk about it is if
you've ever done a renovation or you've built a house, this is a
bit of your roof shout. It's not finished, but we've made a lot of progress, and
you can actually visibly start to feel it.
But it's very, as you know from building a place, it's expensive getting out of
the ground.
And we've put a lot of effort into that, but we're really starting to feel like on
that particular element around the core, we're making great progress.
But of course, I think across a lot of areas like getting to retail and business
for open banking first, as an example of where a little bit of extra
time helped us get ahead. So yeah, I think we're making good progress.
What was the name of the product again?
Oh, for our online savings account.
All right.
Yeah.
And can we get invited to the roof shout?
Always.
Nancy Lou.
Thank you, Chair. And thank you, Steve.
I recall reading an article recently when Kiwibank reported
a drop in profit.
Yep.
Still profit-
Yeah
... but a drop in profit. And I remember a couple of the points mentioned were
including, obviously, the drop in-
In the interest margin. Yep
... interest margin. But also, there was a phrase referring
to the competition, especially coming from the other banks.
Yep.
And ANZ was mentioned. And so I'm keen to hear from
you
the balance between there is too much competition.
Now, obviously, the big guys can afford-
Mm-hmm
... supposedly, a bigger drop in their profit in order to capture a bigger
market. But then it will hurt you as you're trying to grow.
And do you then take it more, do you chase to the bottom?
Yeah. No. Well, we can't because we don't have the scale to be able to do that.
So, I
think more than 80% of the time, we've had the leading rate in the one
year.
Okay.
And 58% of time, we've had the equal leading rate in the two year for loans, for
instance. But ultimately, you have to make decisions that
Ben and Tony run a fantastically successful business.
When cashback was being offered by ANZ, there will be a perfectly logical
reason that they're making that decision.
They will be deciding that the lifetime value of the customer is worth
it, or there's a particular activity that they really want to push at the moment
because they think it works really well, or for whatever reasons.
I don't sit on their desk and know that, but that will be logical.
There's just times where we have to step back because we just don't have that
scale. And if you're making, and you have a balance sheet that big,
you probably can afford to sort of put the foot down sometimes and see whether
people blink.
But banking is a scale game, and we need to continue.
We've doubled in size. We just need to keep getting bigger, and then
hopefully we're the people who continue to put the pressure on that pricing.
I might just close with a couple questions, Steve-
Sure
... if I can. Sorry, we're a bit short for time.
No problems.
I'll wrap two questions together.
What current banking regulations have the greatest compliance cost relative to
the consumer benefit they deliver?
You being a smaller bank, obviously the FinTechs talk about that.
And I'll wrap into another question.
Where you as a challenger bank want to grow your market share, what is the
biggest or important regulatory or structural changes that impede your
ability to be more aggressive?
Oh, I think we saw that, to answer your second question first, the change in risk
weights and the capital requirements was the single biggest time in my eight
years that gave us the best chance to compete more effectively.
So where I think we have seen historical rules that are sort of
don't make any sense under a current environment, Chair, I think those are the ones
that make the most difference. So risk weights and capital settings was the biggest
one that accelerated. The one I'm most sort of worried about is the
deposit compensation scheme and the levies that come with that, which is
we're going to end up with a capital set of rules for assets that work one
way and a set of deposits that work in a different way.
And I think if you think about those levies and how they're going to apply across
the different categories of deposit takers, just be super careful
about what you require from quite small players.
Now, I can understand the type of things that you want when you've got $35
billion worth of deposits. Losing a business that's got that sort of size will
have a massive impact into the community and confidence.
But smaller players who are getting started having the same set of rules as us,
having to comply in the same way, having ways-
So it's proportionality again.
That's exactly right. Yeah. But in that space where you're wanting new entrants-
Yeah
... you have to be careful, and it's a real delicate balancing act.
You have to be careful about what you ask from them for the size that they are.
Steve, thanks so much for coming in.
Mm-hmm.
I really appreciate your candor and your engagement with us.
Thanks for all the great work.
Look forward to the shout.
Yeah.
Thanks, Steve.
And good luck for the next few months.
Thanks very much. Take care.
Thanks, Steve. Thank you.
Thanks for your insights.
Cheers.